This is a snapshot of Dutch soccer fans
doing what Dutch soccer fans do best.
For decades following their national
team, the traveling fans have donned
their orange, assembled by the
thousands, and walked city streets
behind the famed orange bus to the
hosting stadium. And June 20th, 2026 was
no different. Taking public transit and
biking to meet a university campus at
the edge of the host city's museum
district, an estimated 25,000 fans
headed south. Following a residential
avenue, the massive crowd benefited from
the shade of an urban canopy of old
growth oaks lining the roadway.
Daylighting onto Main Street, they then
crossed a waterway bordered by a
pedestrian trail. Now nearing the
stadium, the crowd merged alongside the
path of the city's light rail. Following
the red line southbound, they arrived at
the city's stadium center. Across 3 mi
or 5 km through wooded, fairly compact
neighborhoods, crossing canals and
pedestrian trails, bordering along a
mass transit system, [music]
the route would feel a fairly standard
one for the traveling Dutch fans, aside
from perhaps the heat. Because while the
route doesn't seem so out of the
ordinary for the walking European super
fan, this is Houston, Texas, which, even
within a state known for being
car-obsessed, within a country known for
being car-obsessed, is known by
Americans to be unwalkable, sprawling,
and car-obsessed. What this 3-mi World
Cup jaunt serves to show is that
Houston, along with its home state, are
easy to stereotype and oversimplify, but
on the ground level, they're beginning
to look a little different.
Texas is, of course, booming. But the
U-Haul Growth Index, which simply looks
at the destination of one-way trucks
rented, Texas has been either the number
one or number two most common
destination for movers every year since
2016. And by the ever-so-cliche
indicator that's usually saved for
California, if Texas were its own
country, it'd be the world's eighth
largest by GDP. And you, of course, know
all this. Elon Musk talks about it, Greg
Abbott brags about it, Fox News
showcases it, and the state itself
revels in it. But this Texas-sized
population boom and corresponding
economic miracle is more complicated
than two sides of a highly politicized
representation. While the bedrock has
always been energy and gas exports, it's
more than good old boys racking up
absurd wealth on fossil fuels as the
left would leave you thinking. And while
business relocation and local investment
has pushed the state economy to grow at
a pace faster than most others, it's
more than just a lack of red tape and
conservative values opening up
opportunities as the boosters from the
right would have you to believe. Both
energy and a comparatively pro-business
environment are major contributors, but
Texas has been growing upward for so
long because of something more basic.
It's just a remarkably steady growth
engine that hasn't shown any real signs
of slowing until, perhaps, now.
Steadily growing without really slowing
is a simple concept, but in a world of
finite resources, it's a uniquely
challenging cycle to stimulate and
maintain. And to understand how Texas
just grows and grows, we need to
consider where Texas grows. [music]
This is the Texas triangle. It's along
the three points of this triangle, the
Houston area, the Dallas-Fort Worth
metro area, and the Austin and San
Antonio metro area, where you find the
highest population densities within the
state. And it's along these urban areas'
outskirts where you find the fastest
growing population centers within the
fastest growing state. In line with this
population concentration, this triangle
makes up for 70% of the state's total
population, its relative economic might
as the triangle generates almost 80% of
the state's GDP. And all of this is
driven by the points on the triangle.
Take Houston.
In the 1830s, Texas struck out as its
own country. It wanted its independence
from Mexico, but it wanted to be a
slave-holding state annexed [music] into
the US during a period where annexing a
slave-holding state was a tough
political sell. So, it set off on its
own and it put its capital right here
for the first couple years in Houston
where the Rice, now a residential
building, stands. Well, the independence
of the Republic of Texas wouldn't last
long, a state-wide sense of independence
would.
>> [music]
>> In 1948, a century after the state had
joined the Union, Houston voters bucked
the trend sweeping across most major
cities in the US and voted against
adopting a city-wide zoning ordinance or
a municipal law that would outline what
type of buildings would be built where.
In the next decade, the city doubled in
size and nearly reached [music] a
million inhabitants. And as it crossed
the million member mark in the early
1960s, residents again voted against
zoning ordinances. This legacy has led
to things like this, Huckleberry Circle,
where expensive single-family homes are
abutted by massive apartment towers. It
also made room for things like
never-ending parking lots and this
picture in particular. From the '70s,
this shot has become synonymous with
Houston's car obsession and lack of
central vision in creating a cityscape.
This is the heart of the city, just
blocks away from where the Republic of
Texas capital building once stood. But
again, it's an oversimplification to
call Houston an unwalkable, unplanned
[music] urban disaster. For one, this
same area of downtown has fundamentally
transformed over the last 50 years. It
now looks like this. But more
importantly and more transformatively,
this unique lack of zoning on account of
just not wanting ordinances
unintentionally opened the lane for the
city to become an unrelenting growth
machine. With limited rules outside of
lot minimums in mid-century Houston, the
energy sector boomed and the city
sprawled to a size larger than the
entire London metro area. A big city
built for cars and car parking with
continued demand for more housing then
started to change on account of
opportunistic land developers and
builders.
Since the 1990s, Houston has been
infilling housing and it has created a
virtuous cycle. Take for example this
lot in Northwest Houston. Located in a
quiet residential neighborhood called
Acre Homes, this traditionally would be
a lot for a single family home set a
good bit off the street, perhaps just
like its neighbor across the alleyway.
But instead, a local design and planning
firm had a different idea for the lot.
Rather than one lot, they split it into
four. Rather than a single family home,
it's now slated to serve potentially
four families. At least in theory, this
creates benefits for both developers and
residents. CGEA Planning, rather than
building and selling one larger home
for, say, $400,000, can now build out
and sell four homes for $150,000 each
and make 50% more on sales. And while
turning a profit, they can also be proud
of their community impact. They're
providing four homes to be sold at a
comparatively low price that, through
increasing the neighborhood population
density, helps local business,
incentivizes further business
development, makes the neighborhood more
dynamic and appealing to more
pro-density development, which makes the
area more walkable, more welcoming, more
livable. And it's not just a theory,
it's already happening here. Just look
down the street. All these homes are on
small footprints and they're all cheap.
This phenomena is most acutely felt here
within the I-610 motorway, which rims
the core of the city. In the '90s,
[music] applications to replant big lots
to smaller lots had become so common
that city officials didn't want to deal
with them on a case-by-case basis, so
they dropped minimum lot size from 5,000
square feet to 1,400 feet and reduced
mandatory setbacks of homes from 25 feet
to just 5 feet off the street.
Within this loop, denser and denser
housing has allowed the area to maintain
about 4,500 people living within each
square mile. Nothing crazy in terms of
density, but on par with the likes of
Sacramento, Long Beach, and Atlanta.
Surprisingly, given the city's
reputation, it's becoming more and more
bikeable. While the inner loop has a
fairly high walkability score. But an
uptick in population density and better
walkability scores don't speak to why
Houston has been such a draw in the last
25 years. It's the fact that these
denser housing projects are cheap, too.
Of the 20 largest metro areas in the US,
Houston has the second cheapest housing,
backing its welcoming reputation with
real economic opportunity for new
arrivals. Depending on rankings, Houston
is the US's most diverse or second most
diverse major city. Houston is welcoming
and this is partly due to the city's
heritage. This was, once, Mexico. This
is also a historically black city and
serves as one of the best landing spots
for black professionals with nearly a
fifth of all businesses black-owned and
a professional workforce where about 20%
of teachers and 20% of doctors are
black. It's been a welcoming city to
refugees, whether that's Vietnamese
relocating during the 1970s or the
quarter of a million that were displaced
during Hurricane Katrina. And it's also
structurally welcoming. Thanks to
infill, Houston adds housing and people
without seeing its housing prices shoot
skyward. Because housing and cost of
living is relatively cheap, it's a place
where construction jobs, food and
service jobs, manufacturing jobs can
more than make ends meet. Houston is by
no means perfect. It's fairly segregated
in places, gentrification is pushing out
families in other areas like the Third
Ward. But on the whole, it's a leader in
opportunities for minorities. Infill is
also being matched by overflow as the
Houston suburbs continue to grow, too.
And it's the same thing. Because there's
so much room to grow, there's high
demand, but the supply isn't strained,
so it stays cheap. Because the building
sector keeps humming, the growth machine
keeps running, no matter how hot the
summers get.
Or apparently, how cold the winters get.
Three and a half hours up Interstate 45
from Houston is Dallas. Or really
Dallas, Fort Worth, Arlington, and a
host of suburbs from Plano to Irving
that are putting Houston's growth
numbers to shame. The metro area has
even passed Houston in recent years as
the fourth most populous in the US. And
as far as places for cities to sit, this
place isn't the best. The de facto
capital of North Texas, the Dallas-Fort
Worth area is a southern plain city and
as such it's prone to get hit by the
occasional ice storm during the winter
and will see the occasional snow storm
or two. Once summer hits though, it's
relentlessly hot and muggy, stacking
streaks of 100° F or 38° C days for
weeks on end. And between those two
extremes, when hot happens to run into
cold, there are tornadoes with one
having actually touched down in downtown
Fort Worth in 2000. The weather just
isn't great and as for navigable
waterways around here, practically a
necessity for any major American city,
well, there aren't any of those either.
Not that they didn't try. While Houston
benefits from the navigable Buffalo
Bayou, Port Houston, and buoyancy to
help float its economy, Dallas [music]
has no such advantage. They just have
the Trinity River.
Early city boosters believed that with a
little engineering the Trinity could
connect North Texas to the Gulf and for
a few decades the Army Corps of
Engineers tried but to no avail. But
Dallas, as it is now, was nothing if not
determined. It became a rail hub, it
became a cattle hub, and the area is now
a natural gas hub. Shear will and
boosterism from city founders put Dallas
on the map with little in the way of
physical advantages, the city has
brought in big business by building a
big airport, keeping operational costs
low, and maintaining a large, skilled,
comparatively cheap workforce through
breakneck home building. And now the
area has over 20 Fortune 500 companies
to show for it, only trailing New York
City and Chicago. With Texas
Instruments, Toyota North America,
Charles Schwab, Comerica, AT&T, and
Caterpillar, the area has become a hub
for everything from tech and finance to
heavy machinery. More companies are
coming and more people are too. Now that
it's on the map, the city, as much as
anywhere in the state, has leaned into
its natural geographic advantage.
There's just a lot of flat land around
here.
Less glitzy, less nationally prominent,
less populous and sizable than Dallas,
is Fort Worth. While downtown Dallas is
corporate, Fort Worth has the
stockyards. While Dallas feels
metropolitan with a Texas flair, Fort
Worth just feels like Texas. But long in
Dallas's shadow, Fort Worth is now
stealing headlines. It recently passed
Austin in population, it ranks high
among the nation's fastest growing
cities, and it's on Dallas's heels. The
city is growing fast and really not
showing signs of slowing because of how
it's growing. Conceived in the
mid-century, then built out in the '80s,
the I-820 loop was meant to be a beltway
that surrounded Fort Worth and connected
the city's suburbs. But now the city
limits look like this. Fort Worth spills
out in just about every direction beyond
the confines of the beltway. Fort Worth
is able to add population as fast as
anywhere in the state because it's
adding land just about as fast as
anywhere in the state. Fort Worth is
annexing its suburbs and adding
single-family developments to keep up
with the demands for more housing in the
region. The Terrabella development is
under construction right now, but you
can buy a five-bedroom house for under
$400,000.
Just about anywhere else, that's a
steal, and this one comes with a Fort
Worth address, meaning you'd be living
large in one of America's biggest
>> [music]
>> and fastest-growing cities. But this
development happens to be here. 20 mi
out from downtown, and while it's just a
construction site now, it's planned to
be the most generic of single-family
suburban developments. And yet, somehow,
it's now Fort Worth.
While providing utilities, municipal
services like police and fire will fall
on the city. It's a worthwhile trade-off
because it adds to the tax base in an
important way, through property tax,
while also adding to city housing stock
to at least help keep up with demand.
Because Fort Worth has been an
especially popular destination since
COVID, rents and housing prices have
gone upward, but by national averages,
they're still low [music] and they're
still lower than Dallas's. Which speaks
to another facet as to why Fort Worth is
reaching farther north. They're
following the firms, companies, and
major employers that are moving out of
Dallas and up into the northern suburbs.
AT&T, Fifth Third Bank, Neiman Marcus,
even the professional sports franchises,
[music] the Dallas Stars and Dallas
Mavericks, have left or are planning to
leave downtown Dallas for perhaps not
greener, but cheaper pastures north.
Dallas is cheap by national standards,
Fort Worth is cheap by Dallas standards,
but these counties in the suburbs are
cheap by North Texas standards [music]
and it's proving a major draw. Access to
the city at suburb prices has counties
surrounding the Dallas-Fort Worth metro
area growing by more than 30% in a
decade. It's cheap square footage, new
houses that go up fast, quaint smaller
suburban downtowns with fairly
accessible big cities nearby that have
places like Frisco, Plano, and Irving
booming. Former Californians tickled by
the price tags and lack of taxes, and
former Midwesterners working remote and
searching for a change are now chasing
the Texas dream, while North Texas is
doing everything it can to keep up and
maintain the validity of such a dream.
Where Houston has infill, North Texas
has fully embraced the sprawl. And with
planes and planes to spread across, it
too seems like an engine for stubbornly
steady growth.
But eventually, at some point,
inevitably, unavoidably, there reaches a
limit to the Texas dream. And Austin,
Texas may be ground [music]
zero.
This was the original growth machine.
Tesla, Oracle, Apple, all set up here.
Elon Musk, Joe Rogan, and basically
anyone that was fed up with COVID
policies, coastal red tape restricting
business, or just the plain sky-high
cost of living in Chicago, LA, the Bay
Area, or New York, seem to be taking
their money and their business to
Austin. In-migration had the city
growing at a 4% clip from 2010 to 2020.
Since then, it slowed to about a single
percent a year. Middle-income earners
have stagnated, low-income earners are
leaving as the city has gone from a
weird, sleepy university town to an
increasingly hip tech hub. Picking up
the slack, perhaps creating the slack,
too, are Dripping Springs, Round Rock,
and Liberty Hill, the suburbs where,
again, the city isn't too far, the job
is nearby or within a short commute,
[music] and the dollar goes a little bit
farther than it would in Austin. What
Austin has learned, and what Dallas is
quickly learning, is that the Texas
dream is a mobile one. The Texas
Triangle, the growth machine that fuels
and is fueled by the dream of an easy
commute, a cheap house, a friendly
business environment, and a hopping
economy, is changing in shape. It's
pushing north out of Dallas, it's
pushing into the suburbs of Houston and
Austin, it's filling in between the
cities. For the state, this probably
works. For the new arrival, this
probably works. But, it's putting cities
in a bit of a bind. Any longtime
Austinite will tell you that Austin has
changed. A city that loved the Keep
Austin Weird stickers is just no longer
that weird. It's less steampunk and more
Silicon Valley than ever. That may seem
a privileged problem, or one of taste
rather than substance, but there are
real ramifications. In a state that
taxes pretty lightly, these cities
really count on property taxes, and with
things cooling, Austin is now facing
back-to-back years of a shrinking tax
roll. Recently, on account of low sales
tax revenue, Dallas announced it would
be furloughing some city employees as
its sales tax growth is lagging behind
those in Plano, [music] Frisco, and
Irving. If the Texas dream is a mobile
one, it may prove to be a brushfire,
burning fast across the plains,
following easy fuel, and leaving burn
scars behind. But, as it seems every
Texas booster would want you to believe,
that all may be a problem for tomorrow.
When I started researching Texas for
this video, I was reminded how difficult
it is to understand a place this large
and influential. It's not just that
Texas is complicated, it's that almost
every discussion about it comes with a
different interpretation of what's
actually happening. That's one of the
challenges of making videos like this.
The research is expansive, but the final
explanation has to be concise, which
means constantly deciding which details
are essential and which are simply
interesting. That's one of the reasons
I've kept using Ground News while
researching videos like this since I
first partnered with them in 2023. Their
app and website helps me compare
coverage across hundreds of outlets, see
where the reporting converges or
differs, and build a more complete
picture before drawing my own
conclusions. Just take, for example, the
coverage of a fatal shooting in Houston
by an ICE agent. Ground News shows me
that over 400 outlets covered this
story. Scrolling through, I can quickly
see the political distribution of
coverage, how factual the reporting has
historically been, who owns the outlets,
and even filter by location to compare
local coverage to international
reporting. The left focuses on the use
of deadly force, while the right focuses
on who the victim was and the alleged
circumstances that preceded it. Both
headlines describe the same event, but
they lead readers towards very different
interpretations. That's why I don't rely
on a single outlet or an algorithm that
keeps serving me more of the same.
>> [music]
>> Comparing coverage helps separate the
underlying facts from the framing, but
that's only part of the picture. Just as
important are the stories that never
reach your radar in the first place.
Ground News's Blind Spot feed surfaces
stories receiving significant attention
from one side of the political spectrum,
but comparatively little from the other.
The goal isn't to consume more news,
it's to understand [music] it better.
That's why I've kept using Ground News
for years. It doesn't tell me what to
think, it gives me the context to reach
my own conclusions. It's also
independently run and subscriber funded.
To help you get the most of it, I
partnered with Ground News to offer you
guys 40% off the same unlimited access
advantage plan I use at
ground.news/wendover
or by scanning the QR code on screen.